### From:

#### B. Venkateswara Rao

H-no-25-29/18/36, Sri Sai Nagar, **Mobile**: +918790525176, +8801960-425538

R.C.Puram, Hyderabad-502032. **E-mail**: bvrao570@gmail.com

venkateswararao305@yahoo.com

### To:

The Recruiter/ Managing Director,

**Sub: Application for suitable position** 

Respected Sir,

With this letter and attached resume, I would like to express my sincere interest to work with your esteemed organization.

I am a post graduate in chemistry and have more than 34 years of rich experience in the maize starch and its derivatives Industry. I have been holding responsible positions at the senior level in reputed organizations which employed more than 150 permanent employees involved in manufacturing activities. I have worked around various Indian states and have been abroad for past 5 and half years.

I have sound process knowledge and analytical skills in maize starch and its biproducts, modified starches and dextrin production, quality, maintenance, Effluent Treatment Plants (ETP). Manpower management, Material balance, Yield monitoring, Utilization of Raw materials, Chemicals, water and energy.

I am adept at providing technical support, solving audit and labor issues when necessary. I have a fair knowledge and understanding of current industry best practices and recent technical upgrades and utilize it to company's advantage.

My expertise lies in successful enhancing of operational strategies and managing overall plant functionality to output maximization, cost reduction and achieving production targets. Apart from these I have remarkable experience in Industry operational environment, conflict resolving, employee relationship and disciplinary actions.

I am confident that my vast industry experience and process related skills will be suitable for your growing organization.

In view of the above mentioned facts, I request you to kindly consider my profile and give me an opportunity to work with your organization.

Thank you for your time and consideration.

Yours Truly,

B. Venkateswara Rao.

### **RESUME**

Name : B. Venkateswara Rao

Father's Name : B. SuryaPrakash Rao

Age : 58 years

Nationality : Indian

Languages Known: English, Hindi, Telugu and Bengali.

### **CAREER OBJECTIVE**

I am currently looking for challenging leadership position that will utilize my vast experience along with my management, technical and administrative skills for mutual growth and successful results.

### **EDUCATIONAL QUALIFICATIONS**

COURSE NAME	BOARD	YEAR	DIVISION
BACHELOR OF SCIENCE (B.Sc)	Osmania University	1984	FIRST
( Chemistry, Botany & Zoology)	(Telangana)		
MASTER OF SCIENCE (M.Sc)-	M.P.Bhoj Open	2006	FIRST
(Chemistry)	University (M.P)		

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# 1. July 2019- Feb 2020 as Technical Consultant in Salvo Chemical Industry Ltd (150TPD), Dhaka, Bangladesh.

- Developed and implemented techniques to solve process and quality related difficulties in new plant. Modified and rearranged process pipelines/ tanks for smooth operation.
- Solved maize steeping system problems by reducing steeping time.
- Modified gluten sedimentation system and increased gluten recovery.
- Improvement of Machine and Manpower utilization to maximum possible extent, thus saving power, energy and water and have done several process modifications to enhance efficiency.
- Coordinating and directing Effluent treatment plant activities.

# 2. Feb 2014- Jan 2019 as Plant Manager in MAAR Ltd (50TPD), Shahpur, Bangladesh.

- In charge of overall plant functioning, involving overseeing of day to day manufacturing and improvement activities.
- Responsible for various corrective actions for getting the plant to its maximum production capacity, ensuring high product quality and meeting high standards.
- Responsible for initial commissioning of the plant and training the staff and turning manufacturing process lean and efficient. Also assisted the management in manpower reduction.
- Commissioned and coordinated with respective consultants in successful operation of biological Effluent Treatment Plant (ETP).

# 3. July 2010- Jan 2014 as Plant Manager- M/s Sukhjit Starch Ltd (200TPD Maize processing plant), Nizamabad, Telangana, Punjab & Himachal Pradesh in India.

- Appointed as Head of the Department of Starch, Dextrin & Effluent plants.
- Responsible for Overview of entire operational, technical, manufacturing and staff supervision.

# 4. July 1998 – Aug 2009 as Production Manager – Gayatri Bio Organics Ltd (150TPD), Sangareddy, Telangana, India.

- Head of the Department Starch Division
- Commissioned 150TPD Maize processing plant, achieved commercial yields, effectively trained supervisors and operators.
- Planned scheduled operations, Plant performance, Supervision of total workforce.
- Successful implementation of ISO Audit systems.

# 5. June 1997 – May 1998 as Production Superintendent – M/s Sukhjit Starch Ltd (120TPD), Nizamabad, Telangana, India.

 Responsible for production supervision, Quality control, Yield Monitoring, Personnel management.

# 6. Dec 1995 – May 1997 as Plant Manager – M/s Santosh Maize & Industries Ltd (80TPD), Salem, Tamil Nadu, India.

- Commissioned 80TPD maize processing plant and undertook overall responsibility.
- Gained experience in Kasava plant.

# 7. Jan 1986 – Aug 1995 as Shift Manager – M/s Laxmi Starch Ltd (150TPD), Hyderabad, Telangana, India.

- Promoted from roles of Chemist, Supervisor, Superintendent and then to shift manager.
- Responsible for overview of process parameters, Quality control and assurance.
- Achieved shift wise crushing and production targets of Starch & Glucose plants.

I hereby declare that above mentioned details are true and correct to best of my knowledge.

Yours truly,

B. Venkateswara rao